all right
[Music]
it is now widely accepted that diets
high in animal fat processed foods are
an important risk factor for the
development of type 2 diabetes it's not
just animal fat but animal protein
intake intensifies insulin resistance
which predisposes people to type 2
diabetes no wonder Studies have shown
that elevated consumption of animal
products and low intake of unprocessed
plant Foods increases the risk of not
only cardiovascular disease but diabetes
but of all whole plant foods to pick why
choose oatmeal to treat diabetes which
as I discussed in my last video was used
for the treatment of diabetes before
insulin was discovered we've long known
that higher consumption of whole grains
including oats is associated with a
lower risk of diabetes but you don't
know until you put it to the test
there's been over a dozen randomized
controlled trials looking at the
metabolic effects of Oats intake in
patients with type 2 diabetes and oats
were found to significantly improve both
short-term blood sugar control and
long-term blood sugar control in
addition to lowering cholesterol levels
we think the benefits arise from a
fermentable fiber in oats called
beta-glucan because you can get
cholesterol lowering even if you just
give the oat fiber straight as well as
an improvement in blood sugar control
and insulin sensitivity in both type 2
diabetics as well as type 1 diabetics
how exactly does the fiber do that oh
well we know one of the underlying
cholesterol lowering mechanisms of
oatmeal consumption might be it's
microbiome manipulating ability in other
words having a beneficial effect on our
intestinal bacteria a little Fiber goes
a long way here they were talking about
the anti-inflammatory effects of the
short chain fatty acids that are good
gut Flora make from fiber
there are dozens of randomized
controlled trials showing the types of
fiber found in oats and beans can
improve long-term blood sugar control in
diabetics in fact nearly double the FDA
threshold required for new blood sugar
lowering drugs why because the gut
bacteria is selectively promoted by
dietary fiber intake can help alleviate
type 2 diabetes
in fact on the basis of 50 distinct
bacterial markers of the feces you can
tell who does and does not have diabetes
but change your diet and you can change
your gut Flora within one day we feed
them with fiber and in return they feed
us right back with these short chain
fatty acids like butyrate that have all
these wonderful effects put people on a
diet pack with oats beans fruits
vegetables and nuts and the number of
fiber feeders churning out the
beneficial short chain fatty acids
shoots up and fasting diabetic blood
sugars drop about 25 percent within one
month and the more fiber feeders they
fostered the better their blood sugar
control when the fiber promoted short
chain fatty acid producers were present
in Greater diversity and abundance
participants had better Improvement in
their hemoglobin A1c levels which is a
measure of longer term blood sugar
control
then before and after fecal transplant
studies help nail down cause and effect
the oat fiber itself has been shown to
act as a Prebiotic boosting the growth
of beneficial bacteria like
lactobacillus and bifidobacteria so
between the lack of animal protein lack
of animal fat and bursting at the seams
with Prebiotic fiber it's no wonder that
oatmeal diets grew to become part of the
clinical routine in the treatment of
diabetics however over time this
practice has later become increasingly
forgotten a disappearance that's been
compared to the fate of unpopular
theories and successive editions of
Soviet encyclopedias despite advances in
therapy we still have many people with
poorly controlled diabetes thankfully
this forgotten tool is back I'll review
all the new oatmeal diet studies next
foreign